"The Benefits of Purslane
for Treating Oral Lichen Planus"
There's an inflammatory
autoimmune condition
known as oral lichen planus,
in which our immune system starts
attacking the lining of our mouth.
This is what it looks like.
It's actually not that rare,
it strikes up to five percent
of the population,
particularly women,
and about one percent of cases
can turn into cancer.
There's no cure,
there's just
symptomatic treatments:
steroids, immunosuppressants,
and total glucosides of peony.
Like, peony peony?
Yes, medicinal properties in the
root of the common garden peony.
That's neat.
But are there any edible plants
that may help?
There's a plant called purslane,
one of the most common weeds
in the world—
you can see it growing out
of the cracks in the sidewalk
everywhere you look,
once you start looking.
Its healing properties
were thought to be so reliable
that Roman savant
Pliny the Elder
advised wearing the plant
as an amulet to expel all evil.
I don't know about that.
What about just eating it?
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
found that 83 percent
of those in the purslane group
experienced partial or complete
clinical improvement,
compared to 83 percent
in the placebo group
who either didn't respond
or got worse.
So, this simple weed appears
to be clinically effective
in the treatment
of oral lichen planus,
with no side effects.
In a comparison
to the efficacy and safety
of nine different treatments,
including steroids
and immunosuppressants,
purslane appeared to not only
be the safest,
but the most effective
treatment available,
with only good side-effects:
lowering triglycerides
and decreasing inflammation.
You can overdo it, though.
Purslane is a high oxalate green,
with nearly half as much
oxalates as spinach.
So, even if you don't
tend to get kidney stones,
you don't want to eat four pounds
(2 kg) of purslane at a time.
I know it's delicious,
but as little as a pound and a half
(0.70 kg) at a time,
or even two pounds (0.90 kg)
spread out over two meals
could potentially overload
the kidney and cause damage.
Purslane can even fight
lichen planus topically.
A purslane gel appeared to work
as well as topical steroids,
the gold standard treatment.
The researchers concluded that
purslane is a "magical" herb:
beneficial,
lacking side effects,
and therefore can be
a safer alternative drug
in oral lichen planus treatment.
But by alternative "drug"
they're just talking about a weed
that grows for free all over.